<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Cresko Laboratory</title>
<link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>An evolutionary genomics laboratory at the University of Oregon</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.30</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>LyAndra Lujan defends her dissertation!</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2025-11-20-lujan-defense.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to honorary graduate student member of the Cresko LyAndra Lujan for successfully defending her PhD!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>dissertation</category>
  <category>defense</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>graduate</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2025-11-20-lujan-defense.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/micah-woods.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ethan Contreras Presents at SACNAS</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2025-11-05-contreras-SACNAS.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to undergraduate researcher Ethan Contreras and his mentor Shannon Snyder for his presentation at the annual conference for the Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS)!</p>
<p><img src="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/images/Ethan_SACNAS_2025a.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>presentation</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>undergraduate</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2025-11-05-contreras-SACNAS.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/micah-woods.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Micah Woods Published in Ms. Magazine</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2024-11-15-woods-ms-magazine.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to post-baccalaureate scholar Micah Woods for their work being published in Ms.&nbsp;Magazine!</p>
<p>Micah’s article highlights the incredible contributions of Dr.&nbsp;Kata Karáth and other pioneering women scientists who have shaped our understanding of evolutionary biology and genetics. This publication represents not only excellent science communication but also important work in documenting the history of women in STEM fields.</p>
<section id="about-the-article" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-article">About the Article</h2>
<p>The piece explores how Dr.&nbsp;Karáth’s groundbreaking research has influenced modern genomics, despite facing significant barriers as a woman in science during the mid-20th century. Micah’s careful research and compelling writing bring deserved attention to these often-overlooked contributions.</p>
</section>
<section id="micahs-research" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="micahs-research">Micah’s Research</h2>
<p>In addition to science writing, Micah has been conducting research in our laboratory on: - Population genomics of Oregon stickleback populations - Host-microbiome interactions - Bioinformatic pipeline development</p>
<p>We’re incredibly proud of Micah’s achievement in bringing important stories from the history of science to a broader audience!</p>
<p><a href="https://msmagazine.com/">Read the article in Ms.&nbsp;Magazine →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>undergraduate</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2024-11-15-woods-ms-magazine.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/micah-woods.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bill Cresko Awarded Lorry Lokey Endowed Chair</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2024-10-01-lokey-chair.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Professor Bill Cresko has been awarded a Lorry Lokey Endowed Chair in recognition of the outstanding contributions that he and his laboratory have made to the University of Oregon’s mission.</p>
<p>The Lorry Lokey Endowed Chairs represent one of the highest honors the University can bestow upon its faculty, reserved for scholars who have demonstrated exceptional achievement in their fields.</p>
<p>This recognition celebrates Bill’s many contributions to science and the university:</p>
<ul>
<li>Development of RAD-seq technology and the Stacks software pipeline, now used by thousands of researchers worldwide</li>
<li>Nearly 100 publications advancing our understanding of evolutionary genomics</li>
<li>Service as Associate Vice President of Research and leader of the Presidential Initiative in Data Science</li>
<li>Training dozens of students and postdocs who have gone on to successful careers</li>
<li>Fostering collaborative research across campus and internationally</li>
</ul>
<p>The endowed chair will provide additional resources to support the Cresko Lab’s cutting-edge research in evolutionary genomics and the development of new computational tools for biology.</p>
<p>We thank the Lorry I. Lokey Foundation for their generous support of scientific research and education at the University of Oregon.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2024-10-01-lokey-chair.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/lokey-chair.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Micah Woods Published in Ms. Magazine</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-09-20-woods-ms-magazine.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to post-baccalaureate scholar Micah Woods for their article published in Ms.&nbsp;Magazine!</p>
<p>Micah’s powerful piece highlights the incredible contributions of Dr.&nbsp;Katalin Karikó to the development of mRNA vaccines that saved millions of lives during the COVID-19 pandemic. This publication showcases Micah’s exceptional science writing skills and commitment to amplifying the stories of women in science who have transformed our world.</p>
<section id="about-the-article" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-article">About the Article</h2>
<p>Micah’s article illuminates: - Dr.&nbsp;Karikó’s pioneering mRNA research - Decades of persistence despite funding challenges - The breakthrough that enabled COVID-19 vaccines - Recognition through the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine - Importance of supporting women in science</p>
</section>
<section id="dr.-katalin-karikós-story" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="dr.-katalin-karikós-story">Dr.&nbsp;Katalin Karikó’s Story</h2>
<p>The article chronicles: - Early research on mRNA therapeutics - Years of skepticism from the scientific community - Partnership with Drew Weissman - Key discoveries about modified nucleosides - Ultimate vindication through pandemic response</p>
</section>
<section id="why-this-story-matters" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="why-this-story-matters">Why This Story Matters</h2>
<p>Micah’s article highlights: - Women’s contributions often overlooked in science - Importance of basic research funding - Persistence in the face of adversity - How fundamental discoveries save lives - Need for diverse voices in science</p>
</section>
<section id="science-communication-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="science-communication-excellence">Science Communication Excellence</h2>
<p>The publication demonstrates Micah’s ability to: - Translate complex science for broad audiences - Tell compelling human stories - Connect research to societal impact - Advocate for equity in science - Engage readers with important topics</p>
</section>
<section id="micahs-research-background" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="micahs-research-background">Micah’s Research Background</h2>
<p>In addition to science writing, Micah conducts research on: - Population genomics of stickleback - Host-microbiome interactions - Bioinformatic pipeline development - Data analysis and visualization - Scientific communication strategies</p>
</section>
<section id="post-baccalaureate-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="post-baccalaureate-excellence">Post-Baccalaureate Excellence</h2>
<p>Micah exemplifies the value of post-bac positions for: - Gaining research experience - Developing diverse skill sets - Exploring career paths - Building professional portfolios - Preparing for graduate studies</p>
</section>
<section id="writing-for-social-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="writing-for-social-impact">Writing for Social Impact</h2>
<p>This publication shows how science writing can: - Promote equity and inclusion - Inspire future scientists - Document scientific history - Challenge systemic biases - Create positive change</p>
</section>
<section id="ms.-magazine-platform" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="ms.-magazine-platform">Ms.&nbsp;Magazine Platform</h2>
<p>Publishing in Ms.&nbsp;Magazine: - Reaches diverse, engaged readership - Amplifies women’s achievements - Connects science to social justice - Influences public discourse - Inspires next generation</p>
</section>
<section id="broader-impacts" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="broader-impacts">Broader Impacts</h2>
<p>Micah’s article contributes to: - Public understanding of vaccine science - Recognition of women scientists - Science literacy and engagement - Diversity in STEM narratives - Historical documentation</p>
</section>
<section id="lab-culture" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lab-culture">Lab Culture</h2>
<p>This achievement reflects our commitment to: - Supporting diverse career paths - Encouraging science communication - Promoting equity and inclusion - Celebrating all forms of excellence - Building well-rounded scientists</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2>
<p>Micah’s success in science writing opens doors for: - Additional publications - Science journalism opportunities - Graduate programs in science communication - Policy and advocacy work - Continued research excellence</p>
</section>
<section id="inspiring-others" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="inspiring-others">Inspiring Others</h2>
<p>Micah’s achievement shows undergraduate and post-bac researchers that: - Science careers are diverse - Communication skills are valuable - Their voices matter - Multiple paths to impact exist - Excellence takes many forms</p>
<p>Congratulations Micah on this outstanding publication bringing deserved recognition to a scientific hero!</p>
<p><a href="https://msmagazine.com/2023/09/14/katalin-kariko-covid-19-mrna-vaccine-women-science/">Read Micah’s Article →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>science communication</category>
  <category>post-baccalaureate</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-09-20-woods-ms-magazine.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/woods-ms-magazine.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Host Genetics Shapes Gut Microbiome Diversity</title>
  <dc:creator>Clayton Small &amp; Emily Beck</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-09-15-microbiome-genetics.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our latest paper in <em>mBio</em> demonstrates that host genetic variation significantly influences gut microbiome composition, with implications for understanding host-microbe coevolution.</p>
<section id="key-findings" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2>
<p>Using two genetically divergent stickleback populations maintained in identical laboratory conditions, we found:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Host genotype effects</strong>: Specific genetic variants associated with microbiome composition</li>
<li><strong>High individual variation</strong>: Even siblings showed substantial microbiome differences</li>
<li><strong>Core microbiome</strong>: Certain microbial taxa consistently associated with host genotype</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="technical-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="technical-innovation">Technical Innovation</h2>
<p>The study also established highly reproducible methods for 16S sequencing in fish, addressing a critical need for standardization in microbiome research. Our two-tiered approach achieves &gt;95% reproducibility for abundant taxa.</p>
</section>
<section id="broader-impacts" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="broader-impacts">Broader Impacts</h2>
<p>This work contributes to understanding: - How host evolution shapes associated microbial communities - The heritability of microbiome traits - Potential for microbiome-based therapies</p>
<p><strong>Publication</strong>: Small CM, Beck EA, Currey MC, Tavalire HF, Bassham S, Cresko WA (2023). Host genomic variation shapes gut microbiome diversity in threespine stickleback fish. <em>mBio</em> e0021923.</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.00219-23">Read the paper</a> | <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA903943">Data available on NCBI</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>microbiome</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-09-15-microbiome-genetics.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vithika Goyal Awarded Hui Fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-06-01-goyal-hui-fellowship.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to undergraduate researcher Vithika Goyal for being awarded a Hui Fellowship!</p>
<p>This competitive fellowship will support Vithika’s innovative research studying genetic diversity within and across populations of Bay pipefish in Oregon. Her work contributes to our understanding of population structure and adaptation in these fascinating syngnathid fishes.</p>
<section id="about-the-hui-fellowship" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-hui-fellowship">About the Hui Fellowship</h2>
<p>The Hui Undergraduate Research Fellowship: - Supports outstanding undergraduate research - Provides funding for independent projects - Recognizes research excellence - Enables in-depth scientific investigation - Prepares students for graduate studies</p>
</section>
<section id="vithikas-research-project" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="vithikas-research-project">Vithika’s Research Project</h2>
<p>Vithika is investigating: - Genetic diversity in Oregon Bay pipefish populations - Population structure along the coast - Gene flow between populations - Local adaptation patterns - Conservation genetics implications</p>
</section>
<section id="bay-pipefish-biology" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="bay-pipefish-biology">Bay Pipefish Biology</h2>
<p>Bay pipefish (Syngnathus leptorhynchus) are: - Common in Oregon’s estuaries and bays - Important members of seagrass communities - Exhibiting male pregnancy like all syngnathids - Sensitive to environmental changes - Excellent models for population genetics</p>
</section>
<section id="research-approach" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-approach">Research Approach</h2>
<p>Vithika’s project employs: - Population sampling across Oregon coast - DNA extraction and sequencing - RAD-seq genotyping methods - Population genetic analyses - Bioinformatic pipelines</p>
</section>
<section id="scientific-questions" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="scientific-questions">Scientific Questions</h2>
<p>The research addresses: - How genetically connected are populations? - Is there evidence of local adaptation? - What environmental factors drive differentiation? - How does habitat fragmentation affect gene flow? - What are conservation priorities for these populations?</p>
</section>
<section id="field-work-component" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="field-work-component">Field Work Component</h2>
<p>Vithika’s research includes: - Sampling expeditions to Oregon estuaries - Habitat assessment and documentation - Specimen collection and preservation - Environmental data collection - Collaboration with local researchers</p>
</section>
<section id="laboratory-skills" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="laboratory-skills">Laboratory Skills</h2>
<p>Through this project, Vithika is mastering: - Molecular biology techniques - DNA sequencing preparation - Bioinformatics analysis - Population genetics software - Data visualization methods</p>
</section>
<section id="conservation-relevance" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="conservation-relevance">Conservation Relevance</h2>
<p>This work informs: - Marine protected area design - Habitat conservation priorities - Climate change impact predictions - Ecosystem management strategies - Biodiversity preservation efforts</p>
</section>
<section id="syngnathid-research-program" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="syngnathid-research-program">Syngnathid Research Program</h2>
<p>Vithika’s work contributes to our lab’s: - Comprehensive syngnathid genomics initiative - Understanding of pipefish evolution - Conservation genetics efforts - Training in marine biology - Collaborative research network</p>
</section>
<section id="professional-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="professional-development">Professional Development</h2>
<p>The fellowship enables Vithika to: - Conduct independent research - Present at scientific conferences - Prepare scientific manuscripts - Build professional networks - Strengthen graduate school applications</p>
</section>
<section id="mentorship-team" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="mentorship-team">Mentorship Team</h2>
<p>Vithika receives guidance from: - Faculty advisors - Graduate student mentors - Postdoctoral researchers - Research staff - Collaborative partners</p>
</section>
<section id="expected-outcomes" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="expected-outcomes">Expected Outcomes</h2>
<p>This research will produce: - First population genetic study of Oregon Bay pipefish - Conservation recommendations - Scientific presentations - Potential publication - Foundation for future studies</p>
<p>Congratulations Vithika on this well-deserved fellowship supporting your important conservation genetics research!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>undergraduate</category>
  <category>fellowship</category>
  <category>syngnathids</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-06-01-goyal-hui-fellowship.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/goyal-hui-fellowship.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Walker Meyer Named Knight Campus Undergraduate Scholar</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-05-15-meyer-knight-scholar.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to undergraduate researcher Walker Meyer for being selected as a Knight Campus Undergraduate Scholar!</p>
<p>This prestigious award recognizes Walker’s exceptional research on predator-induced phenotypic plasticity in water fleas (Daphnia). The Knight Campus scholarship provides crucial support for Walker’s innovative project exploring the precise timing of environmental cues that trigger defensive armor development.</p>
<section id="about-the-knight-campus-undergraduate-scholars" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-knight-campus-undergraduate-scholars">About the Knight Campus Undergraduate Scholars</h2>
<p>This program: - Supports exceptional undergraduate research - Provides funding for innovative projects - Connects students with cutting-edge facilities - Fosters interdisciplinary collaboration - Prepares future scientific leaders</p>
</section>
<section id="walkers-research-project" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="walkers-research-project">Walker’s Research Project</h2>
<p>Walker is investigating: - Timing of predator cue exposure in Daphnia development - Induction of defensive armor phenotypes - Critical windows for phenotypic plasticity - Environmental sensing mechanisms - Evolution of adaptive responses</p>
</section>
<section id="why-daphnia" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="why-daphnia">Why Daphnia?</h2>
<p>Water fleas are ideal for this research because: - Clear phenotypic plasticity in response to predators - Rapid generation times - Transparent bodies for observation - Ecological importance in freshwater systems - Model organism for environmental response</p>
</section>
<section id="research-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-innovation">Research Innovation</h2>
<p>Walker’s project explores: - Precise developmental timing of plasticity - Molecular mechanisms of environmental sensing - Cost-benefit tradeoffs of defensive structures - Evolution of inducible defenses - Applications to climate change responses</p>
</section>
<section id="experimental-approach" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="experimental-approach">Experimental Approach</h2>
<p>The research involves: - Controlled predator cue exposures - Time-series developmental analysis - Morphological measurements - Behavioral assays - Statistical modeling</p>
</section>
<section id="knight-campus-resources" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="knight-campus-resources">Knight Campus Resources</h2>
<p>The scholarship provides access to: - State-of-the-art imaging facilities - Advanced molecular biology tools - Computational resources - Interdisciplinary mentorship - Professional development opportunities</p>
</section>
<section id="scientific-significance" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="scientific-significance">Scientific Significance</h2>
<p>This work advances understanding of: - Phenotypic plasticity mechanisms - Environmental adaptation strategies - Developmental biology principles - Ecological interactions - Evolution of defensive traits</p>
</section>
<section id="broader-impacts" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="broader-impacts">Broader Impacts</h2>
<p>Walker’s research has implications for: - Predicting responses to environmental change - Understanding ecosystem dynamics - Conservation biology strategies - Climate change adaptation - Evolutionary developmental biology</p>
</section>
<section id="mentorship-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="mentorship-excellence">Mentorship Excellence</h2>
<p>Walker benefits from: - Direct faculty mentorship - Graduate student collaboration - Peer research community - Knight Campus innovation environment - Cross-disciplinary perspectives</p>
</section>
<section id="academic-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="academic-excellence">Academic Excellence</h2>
<p>Walker’s achievements include: - Strong academic performance - Research presentation skills - Laboratory technique mastery - Scientific writing ability - Collaborative research approach</p>
</section>
<section id="career-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="career-development">Career Development</h2>
<p>This scholarship positions Walker for: - Graduate school success - Research publications - Conference presentations - Professional networking - Scientific career advancement</p>
</section>
<section id="lab-support" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lab-support">Lab Support</h2>
<p>The Cresko Lab provides: - Technical training and expertise - Access to genomic tools - Collaborative research environment - Career guidance and mentorship - Connection to broader research community</p>
<p>Congratulations Walker on this well-deserved recognition of your innovative research!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>undergraduate</category>
  <category>Knight Campus</category>
  <category>scholarship</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2023-05-15-meyer-knight-scholar.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/meyer-knight-scholar.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Publication: Culturally Tailored COVID-19 Intervention for Oregon’s Latinx Communities</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-09-23-covid-latinx-intervention.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Important publication in Frontiers in Public Health describes development of culturally tailored interventions to address COVID-19 disparities!</p>
<p>Bill Cresko joins a collaborative team led by Jennifer Budd in documenting the development and design of interventions specifically tailored to address COVID-19 disparities among Oregon’s Latinx communities, demonstrating the power of community-engaged research during public health emergencies.</p>
<section id="community-partnership" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="community-partnership">Community Partnership</h2>
<p>The research demonstrates: - Community-based participatory approaches - Culturally responsive intervention design - Trust building with marginalized communities - Equitable research practices - Social justice in science</p>
</section>
<section id="covid-19-disparities" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="covid-19-disparities">COVID-19 Disparities</h2>
<p>The work addresses: - Disproportionate pandemic impacts - Healthcare access barriers - Social determinants of health - Structural inequalities - Community resilience</p>
</section>
<section id="intervention-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="intervention-development">Intervention Development</h2>
<p>Key components include: - Culturally appropriate messaging - Language accessibility - Community health workers - Trusted messenger networks - Barrier reduction strategies</p>
</section>
<section id="oregon-focus" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="oregon-focus">Oregon Focus</h2>
<p>The study highlights: - Local community needs - Regional disparities - State-level responses - Community organizations - Grassroots efforts</p>
</section>
<section id="public-health-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="public-health-impact">Public Health Impact</h2>
<p>This research provides: - Evidence-based interventions - Scalable approaches - Policy recommendations - Community empowerment - Health equity advancement</p>
</section>
<section id="methodological-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="methodological-innovation">Methodological Innovation</h2>
<p>The work employs: - Mixed methods approaches - Community engagement strategies - Participatory design - Implementation science - Equity frameworks</p>
</section>
<section id="interdisciplinary-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="interdisciplinary-excellence">Interdisciplinary Excellence</h2>
<p>This collaboration brings together: - Public health expertise - Community organizations - Academic researchers - Healthcare providers - Policy makers</p>
</section>
<section id="lessons-learned" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2>
<p>Key insights include: - Importance of cultural tailoring - Community partnership value - Trust building necessity - Flexibility requirements - Sustainability considerations</p>
</section>
<section id="future-applications" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="future-applications">Future Applications</h2>
<p>This model informs: - Future pandemic responses - Health disparity interventions - Community engagement practices - Equity-centered research - Public health preparedness</p>
<p><a href="{{ site.url }}{{ site.baseurl }}/assets/publications/2022_Budd_FiPH.pdf">Download the paper →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>journal article</category>
  <category>public health</category>
  <category>COVID-19</category>
  <category>community engagement</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-09-23-covid-latinx-intervention.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/covid-latinx-intervention.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bill Cresko Awarded Lorry Lokey Endowed Chair</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-09-16-cresko-lokey-chair.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are thrilled to announce that Dr.&nbsp;Bill Cresko has been awarded the prestigious Lorry Lokey Endowed Chair at the University of Oregon!</p>
<p>This exceptional honor recognizes Bill’s outstanding contributions to the university’s research, teaching, and service missions. The Lokey Chair, supported by an endowment from long-time UO benefactor Lorry Lokey, specifically acknowledges Bill’s transformative impact on the University of Oregon and the broader scientific community.</p>
<section id="about-the-lorry-lokey-chair" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-lorry-lokey-chair">About the Lorry Lokey Chair</h2>
<p>This endowed position: - Recognizes exceptional faculty achievement - Provides permanent support for research and teaching - Honors transformative contributions to UO - Reflects philanthropic investment in excellence - Establishes a lasting legacy of scientific leadership</p>
</section>
<section id="lorry-lokeys-vision" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lorry-lokeys-vision">Lorry Lokey’s Vision</h2>
<p>Mr.&nbsp;Lokey’s generous endowment: - Supports world-class science at Oregon - Recognizes Bill’s specific contributions - Enables continued research innovation - Strengthens UO’s research mission - Demonstrates commitment to scientific excellence</p>
</section>
<section id="bills-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="bills-contributions">Bill’s Contributions</h2>
<p>The chair recognizes Bill’s impact through: - Pioneering research in evolutionary genomics - Training dozens of successful scientists - Leadership in multiple UO initiatives - Building the Knight Campus programs - Advancing Oregon’s research reputation</p>
</section>
<section id="research-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-excellence">Research Excellence</h2>
<p>Bill’s scientific achievements include: - Developing RAD-seq genomics methodology - Establishing stickleback as a genomic model - Over 100 peer-reviewed publications - $60+ million in research funding - International research collaborations</p>
</section>
<section id="educational-leadership" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="educational-leadership">Educational Leadership</h2>
<p>Bill’s teaching and mentoring has: - Trained numerous Ph.D.&nbsp;students - Mentored successful postdoctoral scholars - Taught thousands of undergraduates - Developed innovative curricula - Advanced inclusive education practices</p>
</section>
<section id="institutional-service" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="institutional-service">Institutional Service</h2>
<p>Bill’s leadership roles include: - Director, Center for Biomedical Data Science - Associate Vice President for Research - Knight Campus leadership - Institute of Ecology and Evolution member - Multiple committee contributions</p>
</section>
<section id="knight-campus-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="knight-campus-impact">Knight Campus Impact</h2>
<p>At the Knight Campus, Bill has: - Built interdisciplinary research programs - Fostered innovation and entrepreneurship - Connected basic and applied science - Developed bioengineering initiatives - Created collaborative research spaces</p>
</section>
<section id="recognition-and-awards" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="recognition-and-awards">Recognition and Awards</h2>
<p>This chair adds to Bill’s honors: - AAAS Fellow (2016) - Multiple teaching awards - Research excellence recognitions - Service honors - International speaking invitations</p>
</section>
<section id="endowment-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="endowment-impact">Endowment Impact</h2>
<p>The Lokey Chair enables: - Enhanced research support - Student funding opportunities - Equipment and infrastructure - Collaborative initiatives - Long-term research stability</p>
</section>
<section id="lab-benefits" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lab-benefits">Lab Benefits</h2>
<p>This recognition brings: - Increased visibility for our research - Enhanced recruitment opportunities - Strengthened funding applications - Expanded collaborative potential - Sustained research support</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>With the Lokey Chair, Bill will: - Expand genomics research programs - Train the next generation of scientists - Advance Knight Campus initiatives - Strengthen Oregon’s research profile - Continue scientific innovation</p>
</section>
<section id="gratitude" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="gratitude">Gratitude</h2>
<p>We thank: - Lorry Lokey for his visionary support - University leadership for this recognition - Lab members past and present - Collaborators and colleagues - The entire UO community</p>
<p>Please join us in congratulating Bill on this extraordinary honor that recognizes his exceptional contributions to science and the University of Oregon!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>faculty</category>
  <category>endowed chair</category>
  <category>honor</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-09-16-cresko-lokey-chair.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/cresko-lokey-chair.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Seadragon Genome Research Featured in New York Times</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-07-07-seadragon-nytimes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our groundbreaking research on seadragon genomes has been featured in the New York Times!</p>
<p>The article beautifully captures the wonder of these extraordinary creatures and explains how our genomic research is revealing the secrets behind their distinctive features. This major media coverage brings our syngnathid research to millions of readers worldwide, highlighting the importance of evolutionary genomics.</p>
<section id="the-new-york-times-feature" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="the-new-york-times-feature">The New York Times Feature</h2>
<p>The article highlights: - Unique morphology of seadragons - Our genomic discoveries about their evolution - Loss and modification of key genes - Evolution of elaborate camouflage - Scientific collaboration behind the research</p>
</section>
<section id="our-seadragon-research" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="our-seadragon-research">Our Seadragon Research</h2>
<p>The genomic study revealed: - Gene losses underlying unique body features - Evolution of elaborate leaf-like appendages - Mechanisms behind loss of prehensile tail - Genomic basis of camouflage adaptations - Comparative evolution across syngnathids</p>
</section>
<section id="why-seadragons-matter" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="why-seadragons-matter">Why Seadragons Matter</h2>
<p>These remarkable fish demonstrate: - Extreme morphological innovation - Power of natural selection - Evolution of camouflage strategies - Biodiversity in marine environments - Nature’s creative solutions</p>
</section>
<section id="genomic-discoveries" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="genomic-discoveries">Genomic Discoveries</h2>
<p>Our research identified: - Missing genes for tail grasping ability - Genetic changes underlying appendage development - Evolution of unique skeletal features - Molecular basis of morphological diversity - Patterns of gene loss and modification</p>
</section>
<section id="research-team" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-team">Research Team</h2>
<p>This collaborative work involved: - Multiple years of research effort - International collaboration - Integration of genomics and morphology - Field observations and museum specimens - Cutting-edge sequencing technology</p>
</section>
<section id="media-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="media-impact">Media Impact</h2>
<p>Coverage in the New York Times: - Reaches millions of readers globally - Inspires public interest in evolution - Highlights importance of basic research - Showcases Oregon research excellence - Promotes ocean conservation awareness</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-coverage" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="additional-coverage">Additional Coverage</h2>
<p>The research also featured in: - Phys.org science news - University press releases - Scientific journals - Social media discussions - Educational resources</p>
</section>
<section id="conservation-message" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="conservation-message">Conservation Message</h2>
<p>Media coverage helps communicate: - Threats to seadragon habitats - Importance of marine conservation - Value of biodiversity - Climate change impacts - Need for ocean protection</p>
</section>
<section id="science-communication" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="science-communication">Science Communication</h2>
<p>This coverage demonstrates: - Public fascination with evolution - Importance of engaging science writing - Value of visual storytelling - Connecting research to broader themes - Making genomics accessible</p>
</section>
<section id="educational-value" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="educational-value">Educational Value</h2>
<p>The articles provide: - Teaching materials for classrooms - Examples of evolution in action - Inspiration for young scientists - Public understanding of genomics - Appreciation for marine life</p>
</section>
<section id="research-continuation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-continuation">Research Continuation</h2>
<p>This publicity supports: - Continued funding opportunities - New collaborative partnerships - Expanded research programs - Student recruitment - Public engagement initiatives</p>
<p>We’re thrilled that our seadragon research is capturing imaginations and advancing public understanding of evolution!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/07/07/science/seadragons-leafy-weedy.html">Read the New York Times article →</a></p>
<p><a href="https://phys.org/news/2022-06-sea-dragons-genes-clues-distinctive.html">Read the Phys.org coverage →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>media</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>New York Times</category>
  <category>syngnathids</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-07-07-seadragon-nytimes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/seadragon-nytimes.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Seadragon Genomes Reveal Secrets of Syngnathid Evolution</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-06-28-seadragon-genomes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our collaborative team has published the first high-quality genomes of leafy and weedy seadragons in PNAS, revealing the genomic innovations underlying the spectacular biology of syngnathid fishes.</p>
<section id="evolutionary-marvels" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="evolutionary-marvels">Evolutionary Marvels</h2>
<p>Syngnathid fishes (seahorses, pipefishes, and seadragons) exhibit some of nature’s most remarkable adaptations: - Male pregnancy - unique among vertebrates - Loss of pelvic fins and ribs - Elaborate leaf-like appendages in seadragons - Prehensile tails in seahorses - Absence of stomach and teeth</p>
</section>
<section id="key-genomic-discoveries" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="key-genomic-discoveries">Key Genomic Discoveries</h2>
<p>Our analysis revealed:</p>
<section id="transposable-element-expansion" class="level3">
<h3 data-anchor-id="transposable-element-expansion">Transposable Element Expansion</h3>
<ul>
<li>Seadragon genomes contain 20-25% transposable elements</li>
<li>Higher than other teleost fish (typically 5-10%)</li>
<li>May drive rapid morphological evolution</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="gene-family-evolution" class="level3">
<h3 data-anchor-id="gene-family-evolution">Gene Family Evolution</h3>
<ul>
<li>Loss of genes for stomach development (consistent with anatomy)</li>
<li>Expansion of immune gene families (possibly related to male pregnancy)</li>
<li>Modified developmental gene regulation</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="comparative-insights" class="level3">
<h3 data-anchor-id="comparative-insights">Comparative Insights</h3>
<p>Comparing seadragons with seahorses and pipefish revealed: - Convergent gene losses across lineages - Lineage-specific innovations for unique traits - Rapid evolution of reproductive genes</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="team-effort" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="team-effort">Team Effort</h2>
<p>This project represents six years of collaboration involving: - <strong>Lead authors</strong>: Clayton Small, Hope Healey, Mark Currey - <strong>International partners</strong>: Australia, Germany, Sweden - <strong>Sequencing</strong>: PacBio long-reads plus Hi-C scaffolding - <strong>Computational</strong>: Custom annotation pipeline for non-model organisms</p>
</section>
<section id="conservation-implications" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="conservation-implications">Conservation Implications</h2>
<p>Both seadragon species are near-threatened. Our genomic resources will aid: - Population genetics for conservation management - Understanding adaptive potential - Identifying populations at risk - Informing protection strategies</p>
</section>
<section id="open-data" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="open-data">Open Data</h2>
<p>All data are publicly available: - Genome assemblies on NCBI - Annotation files on FigShare - Analysis code on GitHub - Protocols on protocols.io</p>
<p><strong>Publication</strong>: Small CM, Healey HM, Currey MC, Beck EA, Catchen J, Lin ASP, Cresko WA, Bassham S (2022). Leafy and weedy seadragon genomes connect genic and repetitive DNA features to the extravagant biology of syngnathid fishes. <em>PNAS</em> 119(26):e2119602119.</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2119602119">Read the paper</a> | <a href="https://around.uoregon.edu/">Press release</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>evolution</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-06-28-seadragon-genomes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hope Healey Awarded Prestigious NIH F31 Fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-06-01-healey-f31-fellowship.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Outstanding achievement! Graduate student Hope Healey has been awarded a prestigious NIH Ruth L. Kirschstein F31 Fellowship!</p>
<p>This highly competitive National Research Service Award (NRSA) from the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR) will support Hope’s innovative research for the next three years. The fellowship recognizes Hope’s exceptional potential and the significance of her research using single-cell and CRISPR approaches to understand the evolution of development in syngnathid fishes.</p>
<section id="about-the-f31-fellowship" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-f31-fellowship">About the F31 Fellowship</h2>
<p>The Ruth L. Kirschstein F31 is: - NIH’s premier predoctoral fellowship - Highly competitive with ~20% success rate - Three years of full support - Recognition of exceptional research potential - A launching pad for biomedical research careers</p>
</section>
<section id="hopes-research-program" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="hopes-research-program">Hope’s Research Program</h2>
<p>The fellowship supports investigation of: - Evolution of craniofacial development in syngnathids - Single-cell transcriptomics of head and jaw development - CRISPR functional validation of candidate genes - Comparative developmental biology - Mechanisms underlying morphological diversity</p>
</section>
<section id="why-syngnathids" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="why-syngnathids">Why Syngnathids?</h2>
<p>Seahorses and pipefishes offer unique insights because: - Extreme modifications of vertebrate head structure - Novel feeding mechanisms - Diverse craniofacial morphologies - Evolutionary innovation in jaw development - Relevance to human craniofacial disorders</p>
</section>
<section id="cutting-edge-approaches" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="cutting-edge-approaches">Cutting-Edge Approaches</h2>
<p>Hope’s fellowship combines: - Single-cell RNA sequencing - CRISPR/Cas9 genome editing - Comparative transcriptomics - Advanced imaging techniques - Computational biology methods</p>
</section>
<section id="nidcr-mission-alignment" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="nidcr-mission-alignment">NIDCR Mission Alignment</h2>
<p>This research addresses NIDCR priorities by: - Understanding craniofacial development - Identifying genetic mechanisms of morphogenesis - Providing evolutionary context for human biology - Developing new model systems - Advancing dental and craniofacial research</p>
</section>
<section id="technical-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="technical-innovation">Technical Innovation</h2>
<p>Hope’s work pioneers: - Single-cell methods in non-model organisms - CRISPR applications in syngnathids - Integration of evolution and development - Novel bioinformatic pipelines - Cross-species comparative approaches</p>
</section>
<section id="career-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="career-development">Career Development</h2>
<p>The F31 provides Hope with: - Financial independence for research - Grant writing experience - NIH training opportunities - National recognition - Strong foundation for future funding</p>
</section>
<section id="mentorship-team" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="mentorship-team">Mentorship Team</h2>
<p>Hope’s success reflects excellent mentorship from: - Bill Cresko (Primary Advisor) - Susan Bassham (Co-mentor) - Committee members - Collaborating faculty - Lab community support</p>
</section>
<section id="research-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-impact">Research Impact</h2>
<p>This work will advance understanding of: - Vertebrate head evolution - Developmental constraints and flexibility - Genetic basis of morphological innovation - Evolution of novel phenotypes - Comparative developmental biology</p>
</section>
<section id="building-on-success" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="building-on-success">Building on Success</h2>
<p>This fellowship follows Hope’s: - First-author Genetics publication - Conference presentations - Technical innovations - Collaborative projects - Research excellence</p>
</section>
<section id="lab-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lab-excellence">Lab Excellence</h2>
<p>Hope’s F31 continues our tradition of: - Successful federal grant applications - Supporting graduate student independence - Innovative research programs - Interdisciplinary approaches - Training future leaders</p>
<p>Congratulations Hope on this exceptional achievement! We’re excited to see your groundbreaking research on syngnathid evolution and development!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>graduate student</category>
  <category>fellowship</category>
  <category>NIH</category>
  <category>F31</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-06-01-healey-f31-fellowship.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/healey-f31-fellowship.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Publication: Single-cell Iso-Seq Revolutionizes Genome Annotation</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-healey-single-cell.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Groundbreaking publication in Genetics introduces single-cell Iso-Sequencing for rapid genome annotation!</p>
<p>Hope Healey, Susan Bassham, and Bill Cresko present a revolutionary approach that enables rapid genome annotation specifically optimized for single-cell RNA sequencing analysis. This technical innovation dramatically improves the accuracy and completeness of gene models for single-cell studies.</p>
<section id="technical-breakthrough" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="technical-breakthrough">Technical Breakthrough</h2>
<p>The research achieves: - Single-cell resolution transcript sequencing - Full-length isoform identification - Rapid genome annotation improvement - Enhanced scRNAseq analysis capability - Cell-type specific transcript discovery</p>
</section>
<section id="innovation-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="innovation-impact">Innovation Impact</h2>
<p>Key advances include: - Complete transcript structures - Previously unknown isoforms - Corrected gene boundaries - Cell-specific expression patterns - Improved functional annotation</p>
</section>
<section id="single-cell-revolution" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="single-cell-revolution">Single-cell Revolution</h2>
<p>This work enables: - More accurate cell type identification - Better trajectory analysis - Improved differential expression - Enhanced pathway analysis - Deeper biological insights</p>
</section>
<section id="methodological-excellence" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="methodological-excellence">Methodological Excellence</h2>
<p>The approach combines: - Long-read sequencing technology - Single-cell isolation techniques - Computational pipeline development - Quality control metrics - Validation strategies</p>
</section>
<section id="resource-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="resource-development">Resource Development</h2>
<p>The publication provides: - Updated genome annotations - Analysis pipelines - Quality metrics - Best practices - Community tools</p>
</section>
<section id="stickleback-applications" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="stickleback-applications">Stickleback Applications</h2>
<p>Immediate benefits for: - Developmental studies - Cell atlas projects - Disease modeling - Evolutionary comparisons - Functional genomics</p>
</section>
<section id="broader-significance" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="broader-significance">Broader Significance</h2>
<p>Applications extend to: - Other non-model organisms - Clinical research - Agricultural genomics - Conservation genetics - Biotechnology</p>
</section>
<section id="future-directions" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2>
<p>This enables: - Comprehensive cell atlases - Developmental trajectories - Disease mechanisms - Therapeutic targets - Precision medicine</p>
<p><a href="{{ site.url }}{{ site.baseurl }}/assets/publications/2022_Healey_Genetics.pdf">Download the paper →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>journal article</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>single-cell</category>
  <category>Genetics</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-healey-single-cell.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/single-cell-iso-seq.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Publication: Stickleback as Model for Mito-Nuclear Interactions</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-beck-mito-nuclear.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Important publication in Frontiers in Genetics establishes threespine stickleback as an emerging evolutionary model for studying mito-nuclear interactions!</p>
<p>Emily Beck, Susan Bassham, and Bill Cresko reveal extreme intraspecific divergence in mitochondrial haplotypes, making stickleback an ideal system for understanding how mitochondrial and nuclear genomes co-evolve and interact to maintain cellular function.</p>
<section id="revolutionary-discovery" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="revolutionary-discovery">Revolutionary Discovery</h2>
<p>The research reveals: - Extreme mitochondrial haplotype divergence within species - Potential for mito-nuclear incompatibilities - Natural evolutionary experiments - Model system establishment - Functional interaction opportunities</p>
</section>
<section id="mitochondrial-diversity" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="mitochondrial-diversity">Mitochondrial Diversity</h2>
<p>Key findings include: - Deep divergence between haplotypes - Geographic distribution patterns - Maintenance of ancient lineages - Cytonuclear co-evolution potential - Functional consequences possibilities</p>
</section>
<section id="model-system-advantages" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="model-system-advantages">Model System Advantages</h2>
<p>Stickleback offer: - Natural mitochondrial variation - Controlled breeding capability - Genomic resources availability - Ecological context - Experimental tractability</p>
</section>
<section id="evolutionary-significance" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="evolutionary-significance">Evolutionary Significance</h2>
<p>This work demonstrates: - Mito-nuclear co-evolution importance - Genetic incompatibility evolution - Speciation mechanisms - Hybrid zone dynamics - Adaptation constraints</p>
</section>
<section id="biomedical-relevance" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="biomedical-relevance">Biomedical Relevance</h2>
<p>Applications include: - Mitochondrial disease models - Aging research - Metabolic studies - Fertility investigations - Therapeutic insights</p>
</section>
<section id="comparative-genomics" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="comparative-genomics">Comparative Genomics</h2>
<p>The study provides: - Cross-population comparisons - Sequence divergence analyses - Functional variant identification - Evolutionary rate calculations - Phylogenetic relationships</p>
</section>
<section id="future-research" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="future-research">Future Research</h2>
<p>This enables: - Functional studies of incompatibilities - Hybrid crosses experiments - Metabolic phenotyping - Gene expression analyses - Clinical applications</p>
</section>
<section id="theoretical-contributions" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="theoretical-contributions">Theoretical Contributions</h2>
<p>Advances understanding of: - Cytonuclear evolution - Genetic conflict - Co-adaptation mechanisms - Speciation processes - Genome interactions</p>
<p><a href="{{ site.url }}{{ site.baseurl }}/assets/publications/2022_Beck_FIG.pdf">Download the paper →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>journal article</category>
  <category>mitochondrial genetics</category>
  <category>evolution</category>
  <category>Frontiers in Genetics</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-beck-mito-nuclear.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/mito-nuclear-interactions.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hope Healey Publishes First-Author Paper in Genetics</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-healey-genetics-paper.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to graduate student Hope Healey on her first first-author publication in the prestigious journal Genetics!</p>
<p>Hope’s paper, co-authored with Dr.&nbsp;Susan Bassham, uses single-cell Iso-Seq technology to dramatically improve the annotation of the threespine stickleback genome. This groundbreaking work enables much more efficient single-cell analysis and represents a major technical advance for the stickleback research community.</p>
<section id="about-the-publication" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-publication">About the Publication</h2>
<p>The paper presents: - Revolutionary improvement in genome annotation - Single-cell Iso-Seq methodology for stickleback - Enhanced transcript identification - Improved gene models for single-cell analysis - Resource for the research community</p>
</section>
<section id="technical-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="technical-innovation">Technical Innovation</h2>
<p>Hope’s work achieved: - Full-length transcript sequencing at single-cell resolution - Discovery of previously unknown isoforms - Correction of misannotated genes - Identification of cell-type specific transcripts - Integration with existing genomic resources</p>
</section>
<section id="research-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="research-impact">Research Impact</h2>
<p>This publication enables: - More accurate single-cell RNA sequencing studies - Better understanding of gene expression patterns - Improved functional genomics in stickleback - Enhanced comparative genomics analyses - Accelerated research across multiple labs</p>
</section>
<section id="methodological-advances" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="methodological-advances">Methodological Advances</h2>
<p>The study demonstrates: - Power of long-read sequencing technology - Integration of multiple sequencing platforms - Computational pipelines for transcript discovery - Quality control for genome annotation - Best practices for similar projects</p>
</section>
<section id="community-resource" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="community-resource">Community Resource</h2>
<p>Hope’s work provides: - Publicly available improved annotations - Computational tools for analysis - Protocols for implementation - Database of transcript isoforms - Foundation for future studies</p>
</section>
<section id="single-cell-revolution" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="single-cell-revolution">Single-Cell Revolution</h2>
<p>This work is crucial because: - Single-cell approaches are transforming biology - Accurate annotation is essential for interpretation - Stickleback is a key evolutionary model - Enables cell-type specific studies - Facilitates developmental biology research</p>
</section>
<section id="collaborative-effort" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="collaborative-effort">Collaborative Effort</h2>
<p>The publication reflects: - Mentorship from Susan Bassham - Support from the Cresko Lab team - Collaboration with genomics experts - Integration of diverse expertise - Team science at its best</p>
</section>
<section id="hopes-research-program" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="hopes-research-program">Hope’s Research Program</h2>
<p>This publication advances Hope’s broader research on: - Evolution of craniofacial development - Single-cell analysis of syngnathid fishes - Comparative developmental genomics - CRISPR functional validation - Cell fate specification</p>
</section>
<section id="career-milestone" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="career-milestone">Career Milestone</h2>
<p>First-author publications in Genetics: - Mark significant research contributions - Demonstrate independent thinking - Strengthen graduate school progress - Enhance postdoctoral applications - Build scientific reputation</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>This publication sets the stage for: - Additional high-impact papers - Expanded single-cell studies - New collaborative projects - Technical innovations - Continued excellence</p>
<p>Congratulations Hope and Susan on this outstanding contribution to the field!</p>
<p><a href="{{ site.url }}{{ site.baseurl }}/assets/publications/2022_Healey_Genetics.pdf">Download the paper →</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>graduate student</category>
  <category>journal article</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-04-01-healey-genetics-paper.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/healey-genetics-paper.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Method for Genome Annotation Using Single-Cell Sequencing</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-02-15-single-cell-method.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Hope Healey and Susan Bassham have published an innovative method in <em>Genetics</em> that dramatically improves genome annotation for non-model organisms using single-cell sequencing technologies.</p>
<section id="the-challenge" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="the-challenge">The Challenge</h2>
<p>Genome annotation - identifying genes and their functions - remains a major bottleneck for studying non-model organisms. Traditional methods often miss genes expressed only in specific cell types or developmental stages.</p>
</section>
<section id="our-solution" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="our-solution">Our Solution</h2>
<p>The team developed a pipeline combining: - Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) for cell-type-specific expression - Long-read Iso-Sequencing for full-length transcripts - Custom computational tools for integration</p>
<p>This approach identified hundreds of previously unannotated genes in the threespine stickleback genome, improving our ability to study cell-type-specific gene expression.</p>
</section>
<section id="applications" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="applications">Applications</h2>
<p>The method is particularly valuable for: - Evolutionary developmental biology studies - Understanding cell-type evolution - Improving genome resources for ecological model systems</p>
<p><strong>Publication</strong>: Healey HM, Bassham S, Cresko WA (2022). Single-cell Iso-Sequencing enables rapid genome annotation for scRNAseq analysis. <em>Genetics</em> 220(3):iyac017.</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/genetics/iyac017">Read the paper</a> | <a href="https://github.com/creskolab/sc-isoseq">GitHub repository</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>methods</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2022-02-15-single-cell-method.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Emily Niebergall Awarded Prestigious Goldwater Fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2021-03-30-goldwater-fellowship.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Clark Honors College undergraduate Emily Niebergall, who is working on her thesis in the laboratory with Emily Beck, has been awarded a prestigious Goldwater Fellowship for her outstanding undergraduate research.</p>
<section id="about-the-award" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-the-award">About the Award</h2>
<p>The Barry Goldwater Scholarship is the most prestigious undergraduate award in mathematics, natural sciences, and engineering. Only 410 students nationwide receive this honor each year from a pool of over 5,000 nominees.</p>
</section>
<section id="emilys-research" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="emilys-research">Emily’s Research</h2>
<p>Emily’s thesis project focuses on understanding neutrophil variation between oceanic and freshwater stickleback populations. Using advanced microscopy and genetic techniques, she’s investigating how immune responses evolve as fish adapt to different environments.</p>
<p>Her work contributes to our broader understanding of: - Immune system evolution - Host-pathogen interactions - Rapid adaptation to environmental change</p>
</section>
<section id="a-bright-future" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="a-bright-future">A Bright Future</h2>
<p>Emily plans to pursue a Ph.D.&nbsp;in evolutionary biology, with interests in combining genomics, immunology, and field ecology. The Goldwater Fellowship will provide support for her senior year and help launch her scientific career.</p>
<p>“Emily exemplifies the best of undergraduate research,” says Dr.&nbsp;Cresko. “Her creativity, technical skills, and scientific thinking are already at a graduate level. We’re thrilled to see her recognized with this honor.”</p>
<p>Congratulations, Emily! We look forward to seeing your continued success in science.</p>
<p><a href="https://goldwaterscholarship.gov/">Learn more about the Goldwater Scholarship</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>awards</category>
  <category>undergraduate</category>
  <category>fellowship</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2021-03-30-goldwater-fellowship.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Congratulations to Our New Ph.D. Graduates!</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2020-06-15-thesis-defenses.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re proud to announce that three lab members have successfully defended their Ph.D.&nbsp;dissertations this spring! Despite the challenges of remote defenses during COVID-19, they delivered outstanding presentations of their research.</p>
<section id="dr.-emily-lescak" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="dr.-emily-lescak">Dr.&nbsp;Emily Lescak</h2>
<p><strong>Dissertation</strong>: “Ancient Mitochondrial Lineages and Contemporary Adaptation in Threespine Stickleback”</p>
<p>Emily’s work revealed cryptic mitochondrial diversity in stickleback populations and demonstrated that ancient mtDNA lineages don’t constrain contemporary adaptive evolution. Her research combined phylogenetics, population genomics, and experimental approaches.</p>
<p><strong>Next position</strong>: Research Scientist, Alaska Department of Fish and Game</p>
</section>
<section id="dr.-kristin-alisha-sikkink" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="dr.-kristin-alisha-sikkink">Dr.&nbsp;Kristin Alisha Sikkink</h2>
<p><strong>Dissertation</strong>: “The Evolutionary Genetics of Stress Response Networks”</p>
<p>Kristin discovered that pleiotropy across stress response networks is highly sensitive to environmental conditions, with important implications for understanding evolutionary constraints and adaptation to multiple stressors.</p>
<p><strong>Next position</strong>: Postdoctoral Fellow, University of Minnesota</p>
</section>
<section id="dr.-allison-fuiten" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="dr.-allison-fuiten">Dr.&nbsp;Allison Fuiten</h2>
<p><strong>Dissertation</strong>: “Genomic Architecture of Reproductive Isolation in Stickleback”</p>
<p>Allison’s research identified genomic regions contributing to reproductive barriers between marine and freshwater stickleback, revealing how adaptation can lead to speciation.</p>
<p><strong>Next position</strong>: Data Scientist, 23andMe</p>
</section>
<section id="virtual-celebrations" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="virtual-celebrations">Virtual Celebrations</h2>
<p>While we couldn’t gather in person, we celebrated with: - Virtual defense parties with lab alumni joining from around the world - Socially-distanced champagne toast outside the lab - Commemorative lab t-shirts mailed to each graduate - Video messages from former lab members</p>
</section>
<section id="continuing-the-legacy" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="continuing-the-legacy">Continuing the Legacy</h2>
<p>These three join our growing community of Cresko Lab Ph.D.&nbsp;alumni who are making impacts in academia, government, and industry. Their success reflects not only their individual excellence but also the collaborative spirit of our lab.</p>
<p>“Emily, Kristin, and Allison exemplify the integration of rigorous science with creative thinking that we strive for in the lab,” says Bill Cresko. “We’re excited to watch their continued success in their new positions.”</p>
<p>Congratulations doctors! The Cresko Lab family is proud of you!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>students</category>
  <category>graduation</category>
  <category>achievements</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2020-06-15-thesis-defenses.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Martin Stervander Awarded Prestigious Marie Curie Fellowship</title>
  <dc:creator>Cresko Lab</dc:creator>
  <link>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2020-02-20-stervander-marie-curie.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Exceptional news! Dr.&nbsp;Martin Stervander has been awarded a highly prestigious Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions (MSCA) Individual Fellowship by the European Union!</p>
<p>Martin will spend two years at the Natural History Museum London studying the genomics of flight loss in birds, applying comparative genomics skills developed during his time in the Cresko Lab. His project, titled “The genomic underpinnings of convergent evolution: Repeated loss of flight in island rails, the greatest avian colonizers,” scored in the top 70 of 9,700 evaluated proposals - an extraordinary achievement!</p>
<section id="about-marie-curie-fellowships" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="about-marie-curie-fellowships">About Marie Curie Fellowships</h2>
<p>Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions fellowships are: - Europe’s most prestigious postdoctoral awards - Highly competitive with &lt;10% success rate - Career-defining opportunities for researchers - Pathways to research independence - Recognition of scientific excellence</p>
</section>
<section id="outstanding-achievement" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="outstanding-achievement">Outstanding Achievement</h2>
<p>Martin’s proposal ranking: - Top 70 out of 9,700 proposals evaluated - Top 0.7% of all applications - Exceptional score reflecting innovation and impact - Recognition of world-class research potential - Validation of comparative genomics approach</p>
</section>
<section id="the-research-project" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="the-research-project">The Research Project</h2>
<p>Martin’s fellowship will investigate: - Genomic basis of flight loss in island birds - Convergent evolution across rail species - Repeated colonization of islands - Adaptation to island environments - Evolutionary constraints and possibilities</p>
</section>
<section id="why-rails" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="why-rails">Why Rails?</h2>
<p>Rails are ideal for this study because: - Multiple independent losses of flight - Exceptional island colonizers - Clear evolutionary patterns - Available museum specimens - Important for understanding convergent evolution</p>
</section>
<section id="skills-from-the-cresko-lab" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="skills-from-the-cresko-lab">Skills from the Cresko Lab</h2>
<p>Martin will apply expertise gained here in: - Comparative genomics methodologies - Analyzing morphological evolution - Working with museum specimens - Bioinformatic pipeline development - Integration of development and evolution</p>
</section>
<section id="natural-history-museum-london" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="natural-history-museum-london">Natural History Museum London</h2>
<p>This prestigious institution offers: - World-class ornithology collections - State-of-the-art genomics facilities - Leading evolutionary biologists - Global research networks - Historic scientific collections</p>
</section>
<section id="broader-impact" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="broader-impact">Broader Impact</h2>
<p>This research will advance understanding of: - Mechanisms of convergent evolution - Island biogeography patterns - Conservation of flightless birds - Predictability of evolution - Genomic architecture of complex traits</p>
</section>
<section id="building-bridges" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="building-bridges">Building Bridges</h2>
<p>Martin’s fellowship strengthens connections between: - Cresko Lab and European institutions - Fish and bird genomics communities - US and UK research networks - Museum and university research - Classic and modern evolutionary biology</p>
</section>
<section id="career-development" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="career-development">Career Development</h2>
<p>The Marie Curie Fellowship positions Martin for: - Independent research career - Faculty positions globally - Leading international collaborations - Major research grants - Scientific leadership roles</p>
</section>
<section id="lab-pride" class="level2">
<h2 data-anchor-id="lab-pride">Lab Pride</h2>
<p>Martin’s success reflects: - Quality of postdoctoral training in our lab - International impact of our research - Strength of comparative genomics approach - Success of our alumni</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/MSCA_logo.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>MSCA Logo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Congratulations Martin on this exceptional achievement! We’re proud of your success and excited to see your groundbreaking research on convergent evolution!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>achievement</category>
  <category>postdoc</category>
  <category>fellowship</category>
  <category>Marie Curie</category>
  <category>international</category>
  <guid>https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/2020-02-20-stervander-marie-curie.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://wcresko.github.io/Cresko_Lab_Website/posts/stervander-marie-curie.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
